Hello, my name is Tomas Petricek, and I want to talk about programming through the lens of architecture,
design and urban planning. When we talk about programming, we use quite a lot of different metaphors.
We talk about writing code, as if we were writing any other ordinary piece of text.
We talk about software engineering as if programming was like building bridges.
And I'm going to add architecture, design and urban planning to this vocabulary.
But first, let me explain why does this actually make sense?
Programming is a lot about dealing with complexity. I'm going to refer to Jane Jacobs, who wrote this excellent urban planning book in the 1960s,
The Death and Life of Great American Cities, where she explains exactly why urban planning involves a lot of complexity.
So, Jane Jacobs says we may wish for easier all-purpose analysis and for simpler, magic all-purpose cures,
but wishing cannot change these problems into simpler matters, no matter how much we try to evade the realities and to handle them as something different.
Jane Jacobs very much realises that architecture and urban planning have to deal
with a lot of complexity in the system and programming is very much the same.
That's one of the reasons why I think it's worthwhile looking at what's being done in this field and see what we can learn.
But the interesting thing in Jane Jacobs is that she actually elaborate on what kind of complexity a city is.
What kind of a problem city is?
Jacobs uses or refers to a paper that analyses the history of science and looks at different eras in the history of science,
where science has first learnt how to tackle problems of simplicity, which are problems, where you have a full analytical solution.
So, Newtonian physics, for example, you can fully analyse everything.
More difficult, more challenging problems are problems of disorganised complexity.
So this is things like movement of molecules inside gas where you can't precisely simulate every single molecule.
You can't calculate that, but you can apply some statistical methods to simplify and reduce the problem.
And the most interesting problems in science are things like genes, gene expression.
Those are problems of organised complexity, where you really have a lot of different things going on.
And they're very complex. They're very complex processes. But there is no way to reduce the complexity.
There's no way to get rid of it and abstract it away.
Jane Jacobs points out that understanding cities and urban planning is exactly dealing with these problems of organised complexity.
There's a lot of different processes,
they're all interacting in subtle ways and you just can't reduce or, sort of, abstract away. Just work with average inhabitants of a city.
Now, interestingly, a very similar structure, a very similar categorisation exists about software systems.
And this is due to Dave Parnas, who wrote in 1985 a paper that looks at the US anti-ballistic missile software efforts,
attempts to build a system, and tries to argue why this is very hard or, possibly, why such a system cannot even be built.
He opens the paper by looking at the kind of a problem that software is.
This has a very similar structure to what Jane Jacobs is doing.
Dave Parnas points out that the easiest systems to deal with,
the ones that engineers know how to cope with very well, are analogue systems where they operate within some safe operational range.
And a small change in the inputs will cause a small change in the outputs.
If you know that individual components are well behaved, then you can pretty much understand the whole system.
Now, engineers have also learnt how to build digital systems that are repetitive. An example here is the CPU.
This is a very large system which has lots of lots of different states.
But because it's very repetitive, it's built up from small, repeated components that are simpler.
You can analyse the individual components and then from the analysis of those individual components, make sense of the whole system.
Now, the reason why software is difficult is that software is a problem of organised complexity.
There's a large number of states, but they're not the result of some sort of repetition.
They're just all unique, very different states. And it's not analogue, meaning that a small change
in input can completely change the pattern of their behaviour.
So just like in the case of Jane Jacobs' analysis of cities, here, we have systems that, not only you can't fully analyse them,
but also there's no way to simplify and reduce the complexity. With a lot of effort,
you can fully analyse increasingly bigger software systems.
But once it gets beyond some threshold, it's just going to be too much.
So that's why I think looking at urban planning is a really an interesting perspective,
because it's exactly an area that is already learning, since 1960s, how to deal with the problems where you can't
the complexity of the system.
And Jane Jacobs wrote her book as a response to the developments in urban planning and city planning prior to the 1960s,
Earlier theories, which were always trying to do some sort of simplification.
Her counterpoint to those theories was saying the pseudoscience of city planning and its companion,
the art of city design, have not yet broken with the specious comfort of wishes,
familiar superstitions, oversimplifications and symbols, and have not yet embarked upon the adventure of probing the real world.
Jane Jacobs was really seeing the current theories of the time as something that uses
these oversimplifications that are just not really applicable to the real world.
And when I look at some of the things that we do in programming systems, programming languages,
I think we might be actually still in the era not yet embarked upon the adventure of probing the real world.
Jane Jacobs was referring to various utopian urban planning ideas like Corbusier's Ville Radieuse or Ebenezer Howard's Garden City idea,
which were all coming up with a reasonably, logically sounding, visions of how you organise a city by
grouping various functions together and having large boulevards, where cars can get from any point to any other point.
To balance for that, you'll have lots of different parks. All those theories sounded like they could possibly work, but in practise they didn't.
And what Jane Jacobs was doing was that she was actually looking at cities that do work or places in cities that do work.
Her book is this amazing analysis of little details in two places, in Greenwich Village, in New York and North and in Boston.
She's looking at the street life, as she calls it.
How the fact that there is mix of functions in the city contributes to the safety,
because there's always people walking around from one place to another throughout the whole day.
Her analysis is taking the places that, from her own personal experience, work and looking at why that's the case.
In programming, I think we've got plenty of utopian programming system ideas that are based on a nice idea,
but if you look at some of the some of the analysis that people have done, they actually prove to be more tricky.
Abstraction is one of them. And there's a paper in recent Onward! Essays about fatal abstractions where this actually doesn't work.
We all love information hiding because we think it will help maintainability of our systems,
but again, there are counterexamples where information hiding prevents later evolution of a system.
In programming languages, especially, we all love formal models,
but just like the formal theories of urban planning prior to the 1960s,
the formal models we use are often missing crucial aspects about the programming systems that we're actually dealing with.
So, what is Jane Jacobs' answer to this problem?
How should we actually understand complex systems and how should we design cities that work?
For her, the key idea is really to understand the city as it is, as a real system with all its messiness and complexities.
And she says, in the case of understanding cities, the most important habits of thought are first to think about processes;
second, to work inductively; and third,
to seek for unaverage clues involving very small quantities which reveal the way larger and more average quantities are operating.
Her approach is to look at a very specific thing in the city and analyse it and see what are the more general lessons that we can learn from that.
Her specific example, one that's very nice, is this chain of bookshops that operates all over New York
and it has several branches that are all open until 10pm in the evening,
except for one branch, I believe that was in Brooklyn downtown,
which closes at something like 7pm. And that's one example that illustrates that,
one aspect of the city is very different, because that's where,
nobody is there after 7pm. There's nobody walking around to buy books.
So that one simple example is actually...
Reveals a bigger truth about the system. So my first call to action from this talk is that we should follow
Jane Jacobs and study programming systems that actually work in their full complexity,
starting from the small details that can reveal what is it about a system that really, really makes it work.
And I think it's important to overstep our own assumptions and beliefs
about what are the programming systems that work, because we all have our favourites.
But if you look at some of the interesting technologies that actually are working in the industry like JavaScript,
there might be interesting reasons why that works that are beyond the scope of what we normally talk about in programming languages research.
Another area where I think we can learn from urban planning is related to conceptual coherence,
which is a term coined by Fred Brooks in the Mythical Man-Month. Conceptual coherence is basically this idea that a system is fully comprehensible.
Fred Brooks says that conceptual coherence dictates that the design must proceed from one mind or from a very small number of agreeing,
resonant minds. The point here is that if you are building a large system,
if it is designed by multiple people who will all understand it differently, then it will not be conceptually coherent.
It will not be comprehensible. So there's this sort of mismatch between the user who has to be able to make sense of it,
and potentially a large number of programmers who are building the system.
Or as Fred Brooks says, any product that is sufficiently big must be conceptually coherent to
a single mind of the user, and at the same time, designed by many minds.
So for Fred Brooks, the whole issue is how do you actually design the system so that it all makes sense together?
It's all understandable using some reasonable rules or some logic behind it.
And for him, the issue is that this works if it comes from a single mind,
but once you start building things that are too big for a single mind, then it's harder to achieve.
Now, if you look at cities and urban planning, then there's different kinds of cities.
I have two example maps here. One is more or less conceptually coherent.
So this is Manhattan, New York, where you have the nice, logical grid with street numbers that are easy to understand.
And on the other hand,
I have a map of Prague which has evolved very much through an evolutionary process and has no overall structure,
at least not in the downtown part that you can see here.
Does this mean that making sense of Prague is impossible?
Here I'm going to refer to James Scott's Seeing Like a State.
And Scott points out that the fact that the layout of the city, like Bruges, having developed without any overall design,
lacks consistent geometric logic does not mean that it was at all confusing to its inhabitants.
Scott is looking at the design of cities and urban planning as well.
And he points out that you don't really need that consistency
and coherency to make sense of a city. And in fact,
the relative ineligibility of some urban neighbourhoods has provided a vital margin of political safety from control by outside elites.
So not only is the messiness of a city something that's not a problem to its inhabitants, but in some cases is actually quite valuable.
It's helped them in many ways to confuse the outsiders who are trying to impose various structures and
control over the city. So the lack of coherence isn't necessarily a problem, but of course,
the inhabitants, the people who live in the system have to be able to understand it.
In cities, this is achieved in various ways. One useful analysis of how people actually navigate around cities,
how this works, is a book called The Image of the City by Kevin Lynch.
And in that, Lynch points out that there are various structures in a city like paths or landmarks that are used for navigation.
So you might have a landmark like a castle that's visible from many different parts of the city, and you will immediately know where roughly you are.
You have different districts which are distinguished by a different style of buildings.
You have various paths through the city, which could be a road or a cycle path or something like an underground network.
And I think this is something that's very much relevant to programming systems as well, because if you have a very large software system,
you can't really have this precise map with every single street on a grid to
navigate and understand every single aspect of the system all at once.
But what you might very well have is a system where you know some general districts,
some general parts of it, and you can navigate, you know how to navigate between them.
You know how they're related through something like the metro system in Prague.
And that gives you a basic structure for moving around, getting understanding how different components might relate.
There goes my second call to action of the task,
which is that I think we should start thinking about understandability, not about conceptual coherence.
And by understandability, I really mean something that's much more dynamic then what we see in,
say, conceptual coherence. With conceptual coherence, the idea is you'll read the documentation and then you'll suddenly understand the whole system.
I think understandability is something that can come more from interacting with the system,
from feedback and from a dynamic process where, just like when you live in a city,
you might know some neighbourhood, and when you need to explore some other neighbourhoods, you have ways for doing that.
And I think that might be a much more interesting and useful way of dealing with complexity in large software systems.
The third point I want to talk about is about adaptable software, and this is inspired by Stewart Brand's work on how buildings learn,
which is this analysis of what happens to buildings once they're built,
looking at different kinds of buildings and pointing out that the evolution is different for each of those.
And Stewart Brand starts by pointing out that almost no buildings adapt
well. They're designed not to adopt, budgeted and financed not to, constructed not to,
administered not to, maintained not to, regulated and taxed not to, and even remodelled not to.
But all buildings adapt anyway, however poorly, because the usages in and around them are changing constantly.
And when you read this, I think you will immediately see why I'm bringing this into a discussion about software.
Because software, I think when we design software, we are very often designing it for the situation that we currently have at hand.
Of course, there's various hopes that our programming languages allow the right kind of extensibility,
but we never really know in what directions is the system going to evolve and change.
And of course, just like buildings, software will adapt, however poorly, because the usages and the context and the environment around it is changing.
So what is Stewart Brand saying that we should do?
He's actually talking about different kinds of different kinds of buildings and for different kinds of buildings,
you might have different kinds of strategies.
But one of the, two of the points in the book that I find very interesting that I think are equally
applicable to software are, first, the point that new buildings teach bad maintenance habits.
And that's because when you build a new building, it works, and for several years it will need no maintenance.
And so the inhabitants are going to stop paying attention until eventually things will start breaking.
And then they don't know. They don't have the habits. They don't know how the maintenance should be done.
And I think in software, this is equally relevant.
We do actually have this idea of chaos monkey for developing distributed systems,
which I think is part of the answer here of teaching good maintenance.
The other interesting point made by Stewart Brand is that the maintainability very much depends on materials
He's very much arguing for materials that have this quality that they look bad before they go bad.
So a wooden siding on a house is an example, because when you look at the house,
you will immediately see in what condition the siding is and you will see that
that this is something that's going to break and not work very well,
much earlier than it actually breaks.
And when houses instead get covered with vinyl siding, that is something that looks great.
But you don't see that the surface behind it is slowly rotting.
So this is, I think, an interesting challenge for software. The other interesting point from Stewart Brand is that one particular kind of architecture
that's called vernacular or unselfconscious architecture works quite differently.
This is when you have things like a New England farmhouse,
which is built basically by doing exactly the same thing as all the other farmhouses in the
area with some minor tweaks by the current owner because they have some specific requirements.
But you're always basically following the same structure and making adaptations over the generations.
So that's what you could call design without the reinvention of the farm,
because the basic form always stays the same and it's just small adaptations.
In contrast, when we are building software, we're pretty much always starting by reinventing the form.
That, I think is an interesting opportunity, how could we design software so that we are not reinventing the form from scratch,
but we're sort of adapting or building on what's already there.
And I think this actually does happen in some areas of software engineering.
I think it happens in areas where you have large systems that are mostly evolved or applied by configuration,
by sort of making all those small tweaks, or in systems that make it very easy
to copy paste and reuse existing materials like HyperCard or the 1990s web.
So my third call to action from the talk is to really think about the materials and the
the stuff from which we are building software and invent materials that age well and allow adaptation.
So by that I mean that allow adaptation.
I think that involves a lot of having access to how the thing is built so that it can be modified without having to be completely rewritten.
The question about materials that age well... I don't have a don't have an answer to that one.
So this is still an open question.
So my final point is, how do we actually get to a point where architecture, design and urban planning is the way we think about software.
I think this is already a very nice and very useful way of thinking about software.
But what is it going to take for this to become mainstream?
And here I think we can draw an interesting parallel with the history of software engineering,
where the way of thinking changes not so much when someone comes up with a new idea about how to think about software,
but more when there's some outside external circumstance that makes that change happen.
In 1960s and 70s, the birth of software engineering was really a response to the increasing computer availability when more and more companies
needed to build software and the small number of expert programmers that were available wasn't enough to do that.
So they needed to sort of borrow the factory and production model to come up with a way of building software that scales more.
In 1990s, the various lightweight software development methodologies were again a response to
the fact that various market forces were making software development faster.
You have to build an application to respond to what your competition was doing in a much shorter time frame.
And that required a different thinking about software.
And I think for architecture, design and urban planning, we might just have to wait for another change in the socio-technological context.
So keep an eye on what's happening in the industry.
And hopefully at some point soon there will be a change that really naturally
makes us think of software as more like an architecture, design and urban planning.
Thank you.